Well, get excited, y'all, cuz it's time
to talk about the United States and its
role in World War I. So, if you're ready
to get them brain cows milked neutrality
style, then let's get to it. Okay, so
World War I broke out in Europe in 1914
because of a whole host of complicated
factors, none of which I'm going to
cover here. And that's because this is a
video about how the United States got
involved in the war and what happened as
a result. So, all you really need to
know at this point is that the war was
being waged between two sets of
alliances among European states. On one
side, you had the Central Powers, which
included Germany, Austria-Hungary, and
the Ottoman Empire. on the other side,
you had the Allied Powers, which
included Great Britain, France, Russia,
and then later Italy. And so, when the
war erupted in 1914, President Woodrow
Wilson kept the US out of the war by
proclaiming neutrality, even though he
privately sympathized with and supported
the Allied Powers. Like Wilson had very
little interest in sending Americans to
get mowed down by machine guns in those
nasty trenches. And that means his
policy was essentially, "Not my trench,
not my problem." And what's more, he was
hoping to stay out of the war so that he
could serve as a mediator to broker
peace and maintain freedom to trade with
both sides. But, here's where I tell you
that maintaining that neutrality over
time became very difficult for three
reasons. And I'm stoked to tell you
about what those reasons were, but first
I want to tell you about my APUSH
Heimler Review Guide, which has
everything you need to get an A in your
class and a five on your exam in May.
It's the fastest and sassiest way to
study. So, if that kind of help is what
you need, then check that link in the
description. All right, the first reason
it was hard for Wilson to maintain
neutrality during World War I was
because the US had much tighter economic
relationships with the Allied Nations.
Like, not only did the Allied countries
purchase American goods at a much higher
rate than Central countries, US bankers
had loaned Allied countries billions of
dollars to support the war effort, which
was almost a hundred times what they had
loaned to Germany, for example. But,
then the second and more potent reason
for the neutrality strain was Germany's
policy of unrestricted submarine
warfare. So, German submarines, also
known as U-boats, violated international
laws for warfare by attacking British
ships without first surfacing and
allowing civilians to disembark. But, in
case you've never commanded a submarine
in hostile waters, then let me tell you
that the whole point of a submarine is
to remain submerged and fire on ships
before they even know you're there. Like
if Germans followed that law, then
they'd have to surface first and then
let the ship's commander know that they
were about to get straight blowed up and
could they please evacuate any civilians
on board. And while the Germans were
offering such a courtesy, Brits would
lower their massive guns and blow their
crap up. So you can see why Germans
didn't exactly follow those rules. But
regardless, this policy of unrestricted
submarine warfare became a real problem
for the United States when a German
U-boat attacked a British passenger ship
called the Lusitania in 1950. Germans
justified the attack because although it
was a passenger ship, the Lusitania was
loaded with ammunition bound for Great
Britain. And to be fair, they'd already
warned Americans not to travel on
British ships that carried munitions.
But anyway, the Germans sunk the
ever-loving heck out of that ship
killing over a thousand people among
whom were 128 Americans. Y'all done did
it now.
>> Anyway, this act outraged the American
public, many of whom called for Wilson
to drop the commitment to neutrality and
retaliate. However, Wilson resisted that
urge and was able to secure an agreement
from Germany to cease their U-boat
operations against passenger liners. And
because Germany didn't want to risk the
United States entering the war, they
complied, at least, you know, for a
while. But then the third threat to US
neutrality came in the form of something
called the Zimmerman Telegram. So like
Germany wasn't dumb. They knew that
sinking ships with ties to the United
States was about the easiest way to get
Americans involved in the war and they
very much did not want that. But by
1917, Germany changed course and resumed
their policy of unrestricted submarine
warfare on the belief that they could
hit the allies hard enough and quick
enough to end the war before the US
could mobilize and come in and fight
them. And that whole situation got
Americans all kinds of hot and bothered,
but it was the Zimmerman Telegram that
finally made it all boil over. So in
February of 1917, British intelligence
intercepted a secret telegram from
Germany to Mexico sent from German
Foreign Minister Arthur Zimmerman. And
in it, Germany offered to ally with
Mexico and in the event of a victory by
the Central Powers, Mexico would receive
back all the territory they lost to the
United States after the Mexican-American
War. And if there is one thing you do
not do to Americans, it is threaten to
take land that we took from other
people. Not cool. And that development
was all the more threatening since under
Wilson, the US had already conducted
several military operations in Mexico in
an attempt to change their regimes and
protect American oil interests. And
since the Mexicans were in the midst of
their own revolution for independence,
such foreign incursions created a
heaping pile of resentment against the
US. And therefore, Wilson knew that
Mexico would find Germany's offer
exceedingly enticing as a means of
retribution. And so, that telegram
combined with German U-boats sinking
several US merchant ships finally
created the occasion for Wilson to ask
Congress for a declaration of war
against Germany. And it was a move that
marked a major departure from the US
tradition of remaining uninvolved in
European affairs. Now, Wilson's main
argument for involving the United States
in the Great War was to make the world
safe for democracy. In other words, if
the Central Powers were to triumph, then
the American way of life would face an
existential threat and therefore, it was
a matter of grave importance that they
should be defeated. And like I said
before, Wilson really wanted to play a
significant role in shaping the post-war
order that featured liberal economic and
political this idea gained even more
urgency because in 1917, the Russian
Revolution broke out and now the
communist Bolsheviks were in power. And
by American reckoning, nothing
threatened the safety of democracy like
communism. Okay, so America was all up
in the war now and the truth is you
really only need to know one simple fact
about it. So, point your ear holes this
way. The American Expeditionary Forces
played a relatively limited role in
combat, but even so, US entry into the
war decisively tipped the balance toward
an Allied victory. So, let me just suss
all that out a little bit more. Now,
after the war declaration, the US began
mobilizing for war and to that end,
Congress passed the Selective Service
Act, which amassed an army of about 3
million through a compulsory draft.
However, it took time to gather, and
train, and equip such a force and
therefore, the American Expeditionary
Forces didn't make much of an impact in
the war until 1918. However, once they
finally did arrive, they helped bring
the hammer of victory down uh real hard.
Now, their main contribution came in the
Meuse-Argonne Offensive, in which over a
million US and French soldiers spread
out across the Western Front and pressed
the German forces to the breaking point,
though it cost 50,000 lives, almost
evenly split between the Americans and
Germans. This battle was part of a
larger Allied offensive known as the 100
Days Offensive, which ultimately
resulted in the defeat of the Germans
and the end of the war. And that means
it's time to draw up a treaty and figure
out how to make some peace. Now, nearly
a year before the war had ended, Wilson
was already pitching his vision for a
post-war peace to Congress. It was known
as the 14 Points, and it included many
idealistic goals for the world after the
war, such as self-determination for
colonial subjects and a reduction in
military spending and an international
ban on secret treaties. But, by far the
most important of Wilson's 14 Points was
the provision for a League of Nations,
which would be an international council
for countries to settle their
differences through diplomacy rather
than war, and serve as Wilson's starting
point for the creation of a liberal
world order. Now, as good as all that
sounds on paper, the 14 Points put on
display that Wilson was a little too
idealistic and maybe a touch naive for
the tastes of Britain and France. I
mean, all this let's just hug it out and
never go to war again rhetoric was
coming from a leader whose country was
minimally involved in the conflict and
suffered little damage on the home front
compared to Britain and France. And so,
when it came time to sign the Treaty of
Versailles, the leaders of Britain and
France were in no mood for Wilson's
idealism and instead wanted to make
Germany pay for the damage done in the
war. To that end, the treaty included
three clauses intended to punish Germany
and would ultimately play a significant
role in the outbreak of World War II.
First, the Germans had to agree to pay
reparations to the victors to help
rebuild their respective countries.
Ultimately, this financial burden
combined with a worldwide economic
depression in the 1930s would bring
Germany close to the brink of disaster.
And then second, the treaty required
Germany to dismember much of its
military and its colonial empire so that
they would pose no future threat to
peace. And in that way, Germany would
forever be at the mercy of the hostile
powers surrounding it. And third, the
war guilt clause required Germany to
claim full responsibility for the war.
You know, this had no material effect on
Germany like the previous two
provisions, but it was a national
humiliation that would ultimately give
rise to the Nazi Party in the following
decade. Regardless, the European powers
signed the treaty and settled in for
peace and reconstruction. But, in the
United States, apparently, Wilson forgot
that constitutionally, it's the Senate
that ratifies treaties and not the
president. You see, Wilson hadn't
thought to include any senators in his
treaty negotiations, and when it came to
a vote, senators refused to ratify the
treaty. This refusal had a lot to do
with the treaty's provision for Wilson's
dear baby, the League of Nations. Since
the Constitution granted Congress the
sole power of declaring war, senators
feared that joining such a body had a
strong potential to drag the US into war
without the approval of Congress.
Therefore, because of Wilson's
insistence to act as if all power
belonged to him, the US did not
ultimately join the League of Nations,
which was a serious blow to its
long-term effectiveness. All right, you
can click here to keep watching my other
Unit 7 videos, or you can click here to
grab my A Push Heimler review guide. I
appreciate you coming around, and I'll
catch you on the flip flop. Heimler out.